At
its simplest form, network access control or N
A
is a way to prevent unwanted devices from connecting to a network.
Some N
A systems allow for the installation of required software on
the end user's device to enforce device compliance to policy.
Prior to connecting
a high level example of a NA
AC system is hotel internet access.
Typically a user connecting to the hotel network is required to acknowledge
the acceptable use policy before being allowed to access the internet.
After the user clicks the acknowledge button,
the device is connected to the network that enables internet access.
Some hotels add an additional layer requiring the guest to enter a special
password or a room number and guest name before access is granted.
This prevents abuse by someone who is not a hotel guest and
may even help to track network abuse to a particular user.
A slightly more complex scenario is a business that separates
employee byod devices from corporate owned devices on the network.
If the byod device is pre approved and allowed to connect to the corporate network,
the
NC system can validate the device using a hardware address or installed software
and even check to make sure the antivirus software and operating system
software are up to date before connecting it to the network.
Alternatively,
if it is a personal device not allowed to connect to the corporate network,
it can be redirected to the guest network for
internet access without access to internal corporate resources.